Winslow Roper Hatch papers 1958-1979
George Mason University Special Collections & Archives
Winslow Roper Hatch papers
1958-1979
C0099
George Mason University Special Collections & Archives
1.0 Linear feet (2 boxes)
The Winslow Roper Hatch collection contains essays, letters, and publications on primary, secondary, and post-secondary education, several of which were written by Hatch. The collection also includes papers on parks and old roads.
Hatch, Winslow
Biographical note
Winslow Roper Hatch was born 1908 in Lexington, Massachusetts. He graduated with a Bachelors degree from Dartmouth College in 1930 and received his Ph.D in 1934 from Johns Hopkins University where he was appointed a student assistant for Botany classes. After leaving Johns Hopkins, Hatch served as professor and associate dean at the State College of Washington and in 1955 became Dean of the College of General Education at Boston University. In the 1960s Dr. Hatch worked for the U.S Office of Health, Education and Welfare. Dr. Hatch wrote extensively on education throughout his career publishing works such as "Approach to Independent Study" and "Effectiveness in Teaching," both published 1960 by U.S. Dept. of Health, Education, and Welfare, Office of Education, in 1965 and 1960 respectively. Dr. Hatch passed away in 1980 in Princeton, Massachusetts.
Immediate Source of Acquisition note
Gift of Mrs. Hatch, 1981.
Arrangement note
Documents in this collection are arranged by subject:
Series 1: Education, circa 1958-1970 (Boxes 1-2)
Series 2: Parkland and Roads, circa 1958-1970 (Box 2)
Scope and Contents note
The Winslow Roper Hatch collection contains several essays, letters, and publications on primary, secondary, and post-secondary education, written by Hatch and others in his field. The collection also includes papers on parks and old roads.
Series 1 contains education documents. The majority of the documents date from Hatch's time at the Bureau of Research in Higher Education, and pertain to studies conducted by the bureau. The documents are in varying states of completion including project proposals, literature surveys and working drafts. Included with many of the documents is correspondence relating to the content of the documents, the status of the projects and discussion of previously published material.
Series 2 contains documents relating to parks and old roads in the Fairfax, Virginia, area. Documents in Series 2 include letters relating to the preservation of parkland authored by concerned citizens and correspondence detailing Dr. Hatch's own involvement in researching national parkland. Other documents provide information on trails in Fairfax county parkland and information on the benefits of studying old roads. Also included are documents detailing the historic significance of the areas of Fairfax County parklands.
Access Restrictions
There are no access restrictions.
Related Archival Materials note
Special Collections and Archives also holds collections on Northern Virginia and regional history.
Index Terms
Geographical Names:
Fairfax County (Va.)--History.
Subjects:
Education, Higher.; Transportation, Automotive--United States.
Contents List
- Series 1: Education, circa 1958-1970
  Scope and Contents note
  Series 1 contains essays, project proposals and manuscripts relating to research and developments in higher education, authored by Winslow R. Hatch and colleagues.
  - "New Directions in Elementary and Secondary Education" author Norman D. Kurland, 1965 (Box 1, Folder 1)
    Includes a letter from Kurland to Hatch dated February of 1967, regarding Hatch's request for a copy of the paper.
  - "Developments in Technical and Vocational Education" author Norman Harris, circa 1967 (Box 1, Folder 1)
    Chapter 10 of Higher Education Literature Review Project.
  - "General Education in Liberal Arts Colleges" author Robert T. Blackburn, 1966 (Box 1, Folder 3)
    Includes addendum.
  - "Pathways to Identity" project proposal authored by Robert Rosenthal, 1967 (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - "A Report on Some Experiences in Teaching Performed in the English Department, 1969-1970" (Box 1, Folder 5)
    Includes a letter to Dr. Hatch from Virgil Peterson of West Virginia University regarding the "New Dimension" series, dated September 8th, 1970.
  - "Getting the Job Done -- Improving College Teaching and the Preparation of College Teachers" authored by Winslow R. Hatch, 1961 (Box 1, Folder 6)
    Working draft.
  - Sections 1, 2, 3, 4, 5, 6, of manuscript authored by Joseph Axelrod, 1966 (Box 1, Folder 7)
    Includes a letter from Axelrod to Dr. Hatch regarding sections of Axelrod's manuscript.
  - "An Experimental College Model" authored by Joseph Axelrod., 1967 (Box 1, Folder 8)
  - "Getting the Job Done" authored by Winslow R. Hatch, 1961 (Box 1, Folder 9)
    Working draft with corrections.
  - "The Impact of Institutional Research on the Academic Program" authored by Ernest L. Boyer, 1968 (Box 1, Folder 10)
    Includes a letter from Boyer to Dr. Hatch regarding edits made to Boyer's manuscript.
  - "The Student and Campus Climates of Learning" authored by Mervin B. Freedmen, circa 1967 (Box 1, Folder 11)
  - "Transition from School to College" authored by Norman D. Kurland, 1966 (Box 1, Folder 12)
  - "Transition from School to College" annotated bibliography, 1966 (Box 1, Folder 13)
  - "General Education in the Complex University" authors Sally Cassidy and Alice Haddix, undated (Box 1, Folder 14)
  - Selected Annotated Bibliography for Chapter 10 of U.S.O.E Project, authored by Harris, 1966 (Box 1, Folder 15)
  - "The Examined Curriculum" authored by Max Godberg and Chester L. Neudling, 1960 (Box 2, Folder 1)
  - "Additional Proposed Experimental Colleges" authored by Robert T. Jordan, 1963 (Box 2, File 3)
    Includes two letters from Robert T. Jordan to Dr. Hatch regarding Jordan's work and upcoming publications.
  - Proposal for "The Library College", circa 1962 (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - The "Library College" a Proposal, Undated (Box 2, Folder 5)
  - Manuscript of "Quality in the College" author Winslow R. Hatch, 1963 (Box 2, Folder 6)
  - Manuscript of "The Future Belongs to Those Who Grasp It" author Winslow R. Hatch, undated (Box 2, Folder 7)
    Includes title page through page 248.
  - Manuscript of "The Future Belongs to Those Who Grasp It", appendix and articles authored by Winslow R. Hatch, circa 1950s-1960s (Box 2, Folder 8)
    Includes pages 249 through 295, appendixes A, B, and C, and several articles published by Dr. Hatch.
- Series 2: Parkland and Roads, circa 1958-1970
  Series 2 contains documents relating to Dr. Hatch's involvement with the National Park Service and his initiation of a research and volunteer program focusing on the study of old roads in the parkland.
  - Letter from concerned citizens to the Fairfax Count Park Authority, 1960s (Box 2, Folder 9)
  - "The Critical Decision", Undated (Box 2, Folder 10)
  - "Trail Walks, an Adventure in Community Involvement", Undated (Box 2, Folder 11)
  - Letter from David Richie regarding Winslow Hatch's involvement with the Plimit Run project, 1973 (Box 2, Folder 12)
  - Old Road Scholarship, Undated (Box 2, Folder 13)
    Five pages on the educational benefits of researching old roads, detailing how scholarships on old roads could help us better study history in general.
  - Drafts, Never Instituted, Due to Richie Transfer, 1970s (Box 2, Folder 14)
    Outline for a proposed nature walks program initiated by Dr. Hatch to be conducted along old roads of historic significance.
  - "Discover Your Parks... Public Hearing for Preliminary Master Plan of Chesterbrook Elementary School Site", 1979 (Box 2, Folder 15)
  - Miscellaneous papers dealing with Dr. Hatch's planned nature walk program., 1970s (Box 2, Folder 16)
    Various writings on Dr. Hatch's plans for the Plimit Run project and research on the history of Fairfax Country parklands.
  - Article "Bicentennial America Was a Nation of Participants", circa 1976 (Box 2, Folder 17)